Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- February 1984 - September 1987, Jerusalem: Yeshiva Life and a Start as a Book Publisher, Series XII
  - Book project: Israel's bohemian cafe society, 1940's and 1950's: clippings and information about the period, 1986 (Box 80, Folder 164)
  - Baal Tshuvah/Book project: Rav Aharon Feldman: lectures on the Book of Proverbs. Envelopes for original cassettes, some transcribed and edited; other notes I took from his teachings, both in these lectures and in informal contexts [Rav Feldman was the Rosh Yeshiva [Principal] of Ohr Somayach and one of the greatest rabbis I encountered in the Orthodox Jewish world], 1986 (Box 80, Folder 165-167)
    - Recordings, 6 (Box 175–180)
  - Photograph (photocopy) of Rav Aharon Feldman with Rav Samat [sp?], another Ohr Somayach rabbi, Circa 1986 (Box 80, Folder 168)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Ohr Somayach yeshiva: notes of lectures, by various rabbis, covering weekly Torah portion and holidays; also concerning Jewish values and character building [called in Hebrew "Mussar"], 1984 February-December (Box 80, Folder 169)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Ohr Somayach yeshiva: notes of lectures, by various rabbis, especially Rav Moshe Dombey, on Jewish law [called in Hebrew "Halacha"], 1984 February-December (Box 80, Folder 170)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Ohr Somayach yeshiva: notes of lectures, by various rabbis, covering weekly Torah portion and holidays; also concerning Jewish values and character building [called in Hebrew "Mussar"], 1985 January-December (Box 80, Folder 171)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Ohr Somayach yeshiva: notes of lectures, by various rabbis, especially Rav Moshe Dombey, on Jewish law [called in Hebrew "Halacha"; Rav Dombey's lecture of January 7, 1985, concerns the laws of nudity and exposing sexual parts of the body], 1985 January-December (Box 80, Folder 172)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Ohr Somayach yeshiva: envelopes for original cassettes of lectures [sound quality is poor, but recoverable electronically; also, voices may be pitched too high], 1984, 1986 (Box 80, Folder 173)
    - Recordings, 3
      - Rav Pincus, Musar and "Fooling", 1984 April 3, 5; 1 (Box 181)
      - Rav Pincus, Bais Hillel and Bais Shemmei (side A); 1-120 Shmona Esre? (side B), 1984 April 6, July 8; 1 (Box 182)
      - Rav Perlman, 1986 January; 1 (Box 183)
  - Baal Tshuvah, "Ohr Somayach Leadership Training Program": very detailed exam questions on weekly Torah portions [I was never in this program, nor did I hear it spoken about], 1984-1985 (Box 80, Folder 174)
  - Baal Tshuvah, Dr. Yacov Fogelman: some Torah portion sheets from his famous weekly lectures at the Orthodox Union's Israel Center, Jerusalem; my handwritten notes of his lecture of April 9, 1985; also envelope for one original cassette of Dr. Fogelman lecturing on May 7, 1984, Israeli Independence Day, 1984-1986 (Box 80, Folder 175)
    - Recording, 1 (Box 184)
- September 1987 - February 1991, London Again: Producing Books in Bloomsbury, Series XIII
  -- On September 8, 1987, I moved back to London from Jerusalem. I stayed until February 13, 1991, when I returned to New York. During this time in England I lived in two Georgian flats in Bloomsbury and had a business as a book packager. Book packaging involves developing ideas and dummies for book projects, selling the ideas to publishers and then producing the books, under the publisher's imprint, through the printing and binding stage. I had my own one-man company, Phillips & Company Books, until April 1990, when I joined a large London book packaging firm, Quarto Publishing, where I stayed until December of that year.
  -- I did four books: 1) New illustrated edition of Man Ray's Self Portrait with an Afterword by Juliet Man Ray, fall 1988; 2) Riding the Skies: Classic Posters From the Golden Age of Flying with an Introduction by Jan Morris, spring 1989; 3) a newly condensed and edited illustrated edition of Arabia Deserta by Charles M. Doughty, fall 1989; and In transition: A Paris Anthology with an Introduction by Noël Riley Fitch, spring 1990 (this book was bought for Doubleday by Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis).
  -- September 25, 1987, I moved into a rented flat at 2 Doughty Street, London WC1N 2PH, where I stayed until the next fall. In its own quiet way, Doughty Street is one the best Georgian streets in London. The Spectator magazine was directly across the street from me, and Charles Dickens's house was right up the block.
  -- May 1988, I had my first meeting with Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis at Doubleday in New York.
  -- July 1988, my first book, Self Portrait by Man Ray, was published.
  -- October 1988, I moved next door to 4 Doughty Street, into a flat that I bought, and I remained there until I left England.
  -- Also in October 1988, I went to the Frankfurt Book Fair with a catalogue of book projects to sell to publishers. I went solo, with no booth of my own: my "office" was the coat-check room at the fairgrounds.
  -- In December 1988, my immigration status in Britain was regularized and I was given permission to live and work in the country without any restrictions of any kind. This was a big load off my mind. Had I wanted to, I could eventually have applied for a British passport.
  -- April 1989, my second book, Riding the Skies: Classic Posters From the Golden Age of Flying, was published.
  -- August 1989, my third book, Arabia Deserta, by Charles M. Doughty, was published.
  -- November 17-20, 1989, my friend Lynn MacRitchie and I went for a weekend in East Berlin. It was the week that the Berlin Wall opened.
  -- March 1990, my fourth and last book, In transition: A Paris Anthology, was published.
  -- April 1990, I joined Quarto Publishing, a large London book packaging firm. My brief was to develop my own imprint of high-end books there. I began making sales trips for Quarto to the U.S.A., and was named Director of North American Sales. Those trips took me to America almost every month and gave me a taste for moving back to the States.
  -- September 1990 saw the death of Jerome Gold, Juliet Man Ray's administrator and my great friend since 1973, when he joined the Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective calling himself Crickett Bon Bon.
  -- Also in September 1990, Joyce Block, an artist and my friend since Stanford Summer School (1970), died. I was her executor and heir.
  -- October 1990, I went to the Frankfurt Book Fair, this time not by myself, but as part of Quarto Publishing.
  -- December 1990, my relationship with Quarto dissolved and I decided to move back to New York.
  -- On February 13, 1991, after 10 years overseas, I moved back to New York, where I had not lived since 1972, the summer after college. And with that ends the first installment of the Christopher Phillips Papers.
  -- The book packaging industry in London.
  -- Book publishing and publishers in England, U.S.A. and Europe.
  -- Bloomsbury Publishing Ltd., London, in their very early days. They published my first three books, which were on their earliest lists. Bloomsbury is now huge, thanks to the Harry Potter books, but then they were just starting out.
  -- The making of my four Phillips & Company books at a time when the technology was shifting over to computers.
  -- The great London book designer David Fordham, who was responsible for three of my four books.
  -- Quarto Publishing, the large British book packager, for whom I worked in 1990.
  -- Life in Britain in the waning years of Margaret Thatcher and beyond.
  -- The ripening of Thatcherite yuppiedom, including an important ephemeral book on the "young fogey" phenomenon. See also similar books in Series XI.
  -- Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis: she was the editor at Doubleday who bought my last book, In transition. I first saw her on a selling trip in May 1988, and she wanted to publish Arabia Deserta as well. She loved my work and, before we were on a first-name basis, once blurted out, "Oh, Mr. Phillips... everything you do is so... beautiful!" She made me promise to show her all my book projects first. She alone of all my publishing contacts offered to help me when I was making plans to move back to New York.
  -- Kay Boyle, one of the last of the Paris generation. We had a lively correspondence, and I visited her in California.
  -- Wilfred Thesiger, the last of the great explorers. I got to know him a bit when I needed his blessing and jacket blurb for my new edition of Arabia Deserta.
  -- Juliet Man Ray, Man Ray's widow. There is biographical information about her here, including an oral history cassette I made with her and her brother. She made the new edition of Man Ray Self Portrait possible by giving me carte blanche in Man Ray's studio and darkroom in Paris (now destroyed), which had remained virtually untouched since Man Ray's death, in 1976. There are photographs here of the studio, where I spent many, many hours working with Juliet.
  -- Man Ray: there are many photographs by him and of his artwork, including the ones published in my edition of Self Portrait, and many that have never been published. Many of these photographs were reproduced by me from glass negatives I found in his darkroom.
  -- Correspondence with some of the great surviving B.O.A.C. poster artists of the 1930's, 40's and 50's, to obtain rights and permissions for Riding the Skies.
  -- My work with the author Jan Morris on Riding the Skies.
  -- Vintage photographs of Arabia and bedouin life, by Gertrude Bell and others. Many of these photographs were not included in my edition of Arabia Deserta, and have still never been published.
  -- Correspondence about rights and permissions with writers and artists (or their heirs or agents) whose work had appeared in transition, the greatest of the English-language magazines published in Paris in the 1920's and 30's.
  -- The process of tracking down holders of rights for dead writers and artists in the days before the Internet or e-mail.
  -- The Israeli Women of Achievement book proposal by the Jerusalem sociologist Beverly Mizrachi contains many valuable oral history cassettes with these prominent Israeli women and a short book about them by Beverly Mizrachi published by the American Jewish Committee.
  -- Frankfurt Book Fairs, 1988 and 1990.
  -- London property market, rentals and sales, 1987 and 1988.
  -- Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, Los Angeles (1973-75). Close contacts with Jeff B. Richards and especially with Jerome Gold (originally met as Crickett Bon Bon), who was at this time Juliet Man Ray's administrator in Paris.
  -- A visit to East Berlin the week the Berlin Wall opened.
  -- Gay files (14), including material from England, U.S.A., Barcelona and Taiwan. Some material about the artist Philip Core and writer and performance artist Neil Bartlett.
  -- AIDS and H.I.V. attitudes in England in the 1980's, as evidenced by a routine form letter and questionnaire sent to me as part of an application for a life insurance policy (a requirement for getting a mortgage in England); it asked about homosexual activity and whether I had received an H.I.V. test (positive or negative) or even any medical advice about any sexually transmitted disease.
  -- The world of gay personal ads before the days of the Internet.
  -- The loneliness of running a one-man business in a foreign country all by myself, made all the worse by my total lack of experience in book publishing and the dramatic fall of the dollar against the pound my first week back in London. This experience was, in a way, a culmination of my tendency toward grand schemes and my habit of running before I could walk.
  -- London in its transition from 1980's boom to early-1990's economic slump.
  -- The definitive end (so far, at least) of my on-again off-again love affair with London.
  -- My rediscovery, on my constant selling trips, of the pleasure of being in the United States and of the value of living not in a foreign country but in one's native place, especially when that native place happens to be New York City.
  1) Files for individual books and book ideas, and for certain individuals (Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Kay Boyle and Wilfred Thesiger), are grouped together at the end of the series.
  2) During this period there were always several book projects going on at once, some in the selling, editing or production stages, some just being developed as ideas. For an understanding of most of my day-to-day activities, please see the files for individual books and book ideas.
  3) A note on accents. As I did in my last London period, 1982-84, I kept my American accent intact, without letting a trace of British creep in. There is nothing that sounds worse than an American with a fake British overlay. Plus, sounding American put me automatically outside the British class system and the straight-jacket that imposes. However, I went completely to British spellings and words for things and the British dating system, which I had to, since I was an editor and had a British-based company. I had been using British forms basically since I left America to go to Hong Kong in 1981.
  4) Originals of photocopied photographs from the Jim Ito Collection are in the possession of James A. Ito, 1991 North Alexandria Avenue, Los Angeles 90027; (323) 664-4316. Each album page or photo used has a number that corresponds to a page in his albums.
  5) It is worth emphasizing that I do not own copyright to the photographs by Man Ray and others in these files.
  6) Note the lower-case "t" in the name of the magazine transition.
  - Gallery of photographs (photocopies) from the period [others are found in their respective sections], 1987-1991 (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Photograph (photocopy) of me as the Mona Lisa. Also, a letter by me in which I made the portrait into stationery with the caption "Le Fondateur", Circa 1987 (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Cartoons and funny things I read or heard: includes the funniest cover ever from Private Eye magazine, for the Queen Mother's 90th birthday, 1987-91 (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Relevant pages in my passport prior to May 1988, when my new passport was issued [photocopy: the original is in Series XI], 1987-1988 (Box 81, Folder 4)
  - The "Take to England" working file I carried with me to London. [Also originally in this file were some Man Ray Self Portrait production papers and 1982 ideas lists for my Telegraph Sunday Magazine days, along with lists of writers and photographers from 1982-84; these are now filed in their appropriate places.], 1987 September 8 (Box 81, Folder 5)
  - "Cookie jar" of book ideas I took with me to England, with some later additions [when I would get an idea I would jot it down on a slip of paper and put it aside so I'd always have a supply to dip into], 1987 September 8 (Box 81, Folder 6)
  - Samples of book production and printing cost estimate sheets I brought with me to England, with some later additions, 1987 (Box 81, Folder 7)
  - Samples of publishing contracts, including the Book Packagers Association model contract and material from a December 1987 class in London on rights and contracts (Box 81, Folder 8)
  - Appointment book, September 1987-September 1988. [This is The Jerusalem Desk Calendar that I helped my Jerusalem friend Genya Markon copy edit], 1987 September-1988 September (Box 81, Folder 9)
  - Pocket Notebooks (2), 1987 September-November (Box 81, Folder 10)
  - London property market: listings, with prices, of flats to rent [the document wallet they are in is the one I carried all over London when I was house hunting], 1987 September (Box 81, Folder 11)
  - The ripening of the yuppie phenomenon in late-Thatcherite Britain: The Young Fogey Handbook, edited by Suzanne Lowry [1985], an ephemeral paperback humor book. The photograph on Page 9 was taken in front of The Spectator magazine, directly across from my flat in Doughty Street, Bloomsbury. See also The Official Sloane Ranger Handbook and The Complete Naff Guide in Series XI, 1985-1991 (Box 81, Folder 12)
  - Letters, life and work as I got settled during my first days back in London: before I found my flat, I stayed at London House, an academic residence hall in Mecklenburgh Square, London W.C.1, which, by coincidence, was about a block away from where I ended up living, 1987 September 8-24 (Box 81, Folder 13)
  - Renting 2 Doughty Street, Flat 5, London WC1N 2PH, where I moved on Friday September 25: floor plan; inventory of contents and initial bill; photograph (photocopy) of outside of this Georgian building, with my flat identified, 1987 September (Box 81, Folder 14)
  - Phillips & Company Books stationery, including compliments slips, labels and business cards, from 2 Doughty Street; also includes the elegant French tissue-paper-lined doublée envelopes I used for business letters, 1987 September-1988 October (Box 81, Folder 15)
  - Letters, life and work. [While the Man Ray book was being produced, my work was beginning on my second book, Riding the Skies: Classic Posters From the Golden Age of Flying. The new project started with visits to the British Airways archive and poster collection at Heathrow Airport and continued until spring 1989], 1987 September 25-October 31 (Box 82, Folder 16-18)
  - List of book plans or ideas underway as of this date, 1987 September 27 (Box 82, Folder 19)
  - Ledger book [with strange double cover] that I started but didn't keep to terribly assiduously, 1987 September-December (Box 82, Folder 20)
  - International Herald Tribune, 100th anniversary special issue, 1987 October 3 (Box 82, Folder 21)
  - Gay: Neil Bartlett, Vision of Love Revealed in Sleep, performance piece loosely based on the gay Jewish Victorian painter Simeon Solomon, which I saw on Oct. 27; also, a later magazine article about him and note written by me. See more Neil Bartlett material later in this series. [Gay researchers, note! This play and this performer are important] Folder also contains some other Simeon Solomon photographs in a London gallery brochure from 1990, 1987 October (Box 82, Folder 22)
  - Letters, life and work: includes personals ad and replies, 1987 November (Box 82, Folder 23-25)
  - Letters, life and work, 1987 December (Box 83, Folder 26-27)
  - 1987 financial: taxes, and receipts, which give a good idea of day-to-day doings [material here also relates to Series XII], 1987 January-December (Box 83, Folder 28-29)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 January (Box 83, Folder 30-31)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 February (Box 84, Folder 32-33)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 March (Box 84, Folder 34-35)
  - Flier for sale of the family house in Truro, Cape Cod, Mass., 1988 March (Box 84, Folder 36)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 April (Box 84, Folder 37-38)
  - Letters, life and work, except New York trip, 1988 May (Box 84, Folder 39)
  - New York selling trip for Riding the Skies and Arabia Deserta: includes my first meeting with Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis at Doubleday, May 11, after which I made a few personal notes. [Copies of all Jacqueline Onassis material is in her own file]; my daily calendar is on a sheet of paper, 1988 May 7-19 (Box 85, Folder 40)
  - Passport #7, issued in New York, 1988 May 13-1998 (Box 85, Folder 41)
  - Letters, life and work: the week of June 5, I was in Estella, Navarra, Spain, to see my first book on the printing press, followed by a visit to Jerome Gold in Paris, 1988 June (Box 85, Folder 42)
  - Letters, life and work: includes Jim Ito's photographs (photocopies) of our trip to Florence and Tuscany; also a blank soft floppy computer disc, now a thing of the past, 1988 July (Box 85, Folder 43)
  - The Publication of Book #1: Self Portrait by Man Ray, with an Afterword by Juliet Man Ray [Little, Brown, New York Graphic Society Books, $35]; design by David Fordham. The British edition [Bloomsbury Publishing, £25], was identical except that the jacket's lamination was matte, not glossy. A copy of the book, 1988 July (Box 85, Folder 44)
  - List of people to whom I sent the Man Ray book, with copies I made of some of my flyleaf inscriptions [postage to U.S.A. cost £9.40 each!]. Included here are most of the people I knew and/or was working with in several countries, 1988 (Box 85, Folder 45)
  - Letters, life and work: at this time I was heavily involved with locating B.O.A.C. poster artists from the 1930's, 40's and 50's to clear rights and permissions for Riding the Skies, 1988 August (Box 85, Folder 46-47)
  - London property market: real-estate listings, flats for sale, 1988 August (Box 86, Folder 48)
  - My new flat at 4 Doughty Street [8 Pemberton House, 3-4 Doughty Street, London WC1N 2PH]. Documents relating to purchase, inspection, surveys, deed, mortgage, subsequent ground rent, upkeep and repairs [this flat was next door to the one I rented for the first year], 1988 August-1991 February (Box 86, Folder 49-50)
  - My new flat: floor plan; labeled photograph (photocopy) of the building taken from the street; artist's sketch of The Spectator magazine's building, an identical Georgian house directly across the street [see also a list of notable points about the flat that I wrote in December 1990 when I put it up for sale], 1988 August-1991 February (Box 86, Folder 51)
  - Appointment book, autumn only: this is the last of the Jerusalem ones, which ran from Rosh Hashanah to Rosh Hashanah: I then switched over to regular January-December books, 1988 September-December (Box 86, Folder 52)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 September (Box 86, Folder 53-54)
  - Change of address postcard for the move from No. 2 to No. 4 Doughty Street: printed postcard showing a B.O.A.C. poster by Abram Games that I used in Riding the Skies [my first night in the new flat was October 26; Edoardo "the Italian moose," with whom I was starting an involvement, was there], 1988 October (Box 86, Folder 55)
  - New Phillips & Company stationery, 4 Doughty Street, London WC1N 2PH; Tel: 01-405-4301; fax 01-242-9159; telex 262433 REF 6454 [I never used the telex], 1988-1991 (Box 86, Folder 56)
  - Four things that I displayed on the walls at 4 Doughty Street, 1988-1991 (Box 86, Folder 57)
  - Letters, life and work, 1988 October (Box 86, Folder 58)
  - Phillips & Company catalogue of book proposals for the Frankfurt Book Fair 1988; 23 titles, 10 pages, 1988 October (Box 87, Folder 59)
  - Frankfurt Book Fair: includes my day-to-day timetable on sheets of paper [I went solo, without a booth my only "office" was the coat-check room at the fairgrounds], 1988 October 5-9 (Box 87, Folder 60)
  - Radio interview with me on Radio Nederland, the Dutch overseas service, about Man Ray Self Portrait, 1988 October
    - Envelope (Box 87, Folder 61)
    - Recording, 1 (Box 87A)
  - Corry Theegarten-Schlotterer, my Munich-based agent for European rights, except Scandinavia: correspondence on various projects, 1988-1989 (Box 87, Folder 62)
  - Letters, life and work: includes documents relating to my trip to Trenta, Italy, the week of November 21, to print my second book, Riding the Skies, 1988 November (Box 87, Folder 63-64)
  - U.S.A. trip: New York; Washington, to meet Juliet Man Ray and Jerome Gold at the opening party, organized by Jerry on behalf of the Man Ray Trust, for the Man Ray retrospective at the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of American Art; Los Angeles, including photographs (photocopies); San Francisco. Includes day-by-day rundown of activities, 1988 November 30-December 27 (Box 87, Folder 65)
  - Phillips & Company "corporate" papers [these were never fully executed, so I was never actually incorporated.], 1988 December (Box 87, Folder 66)
  - My British immigration papers, arranged at the British Consulate in Los Angeles on the December 1988 trip [it was a big load off my mind to get this straightened out] (Box 87, Folder 67)